Okay, welcome to this session of Nuts and
Bolts where we're going to talk about business models
or venture models. Bob Jones the other
night talked to you about finding your customer,
and if you remember how he did that
with his guitar lesson example, he looked at different
customers, different pricing points. That's the
beginning of what a business model is.
The model says how are you going to make
money or how are you going to develop a sustainable
business? And tonight to tell us about that we
have Rich Kivel who has been a serial healthcare
entrepreneur and an investor and has seen
many business models over the years. So Rich,
I'm just going to turn it right
over to you and take it from here.
Thank you, Joe.
Perfect. Good evening, everybody.
Thank you.
I'm going to start with you, Rich.
Thank you, Bob.
Hi, everybody. This is a fun topic
because it actually gets into the nitty-gritty of
how do companies make money? How do
you think about bringing the product, the invention,
the technology, the idea, the service
that you're ultimately thinking about building,
how do you ultimately get it to a
point where you're able to generate revenue and ultimately
returns for your investors, whether that
be your venture investors or strategic partners
or maybe you angel funded your company?
And you really have yourself and a couple
of friends that really want to make something
special have an impact. So I'm going to
talk a little bit about business models, just my
background real quick. The whole first part of
my career was on the operating side of
companies, so sales, marketing, partnerships. The first
time I became CEO was a long time
ago when Joe and I actually met. It was an
MIT spin out. It was actually a pretty big thing.
It was an MIT spin out. I was doing a lot
of business back then and I spent a lot of time
working with folks from the business side. And
I found that the business model was a
lot more collaborative than the business model. So
I started out with a business model that
It was actually a company that
had won the MIT Business Plan
Competition.
And a couple of years later, after I
exited a technology company, I
got a call by the investors.
And they were looking for somebody to run this company.
They had a whole bunch of incredibly smart engineers
and physicists and others.
And they needed somebody that had operations experience,
how to build the business model.
This was back in the
days of the Human Genome Project,
for those of you that
are in the life science area.
Just show a hand, sort of life science people here,
health care, biotech, tech tech,
hard tech, deep tech, robotics.
Excellent.
What other areas are you guys in?
Software?
Yep, so SaaS platforms, big data, analytics.
What else?
Oh, fantastic.
Any specific realm?
Geothermal.
Excellent.
Good.
So essentially, when I got involved with this company,
it was basically a
company doing software called Bioinformatics.
They were building software that would allow scientists
and researchers working on the Human Genome Project
to communicate with all of
the instruments in their lab, which
nowadays we just simply take for granted.
You plug in, just like your printer in your office,
you plug it into the wall,
it shows up on your iPhone,
and it shows up on
your computer, and everything is simple.
But back then, when somebody sitting here,
across the street or diagonally down the street from us,
at the Whitehead Institute or the Broad Institute,
were doing research, everything in
their lab essentially was autonomous.
So you got a new pin tool robot or micro-arrayer,
and it showed up with its own computer
and a tower of sort of a computer stack,
and a screen and a keyboard and
a mouse, and it ran its own software.
And then you would go down
to the refrigerator, and you'd see, like,
there's a computer in the back of
the lab, and it's running its own software.
And then you would go down
to the refrigerator, and you'd see, like,
there's a computer in the back of
the lab, and it's running its own software.
That was a barcode scanning
refrigerator with all your samples,
and that refrigerator had its own computer.
And then the scanner, the
robot, everything was running autonomously.
So engineers were essentially put
in a position, and scientists,
where they had to build Excel
spreadsheets to track all of this data.
So, you know, import, export, just constant chaos.
And that became more and more difficult,
as you can imagine, as the machines,
the instruments, as we called
them, the robotics and the scanners,
started taking so much more data.
It was easy when you had a small microtiter plate,
and you had a little pin tool robot
putting a little DNA sample into a well,
and then it would show up once you imaged it.
But that's really hard to do when
you're doing tens of thousands or millions
of data points at once.
So our software essentially figured out
how to communicate with all the instruments,
writing APIs, things that we all take for granted now,
and then helping downstream.
So step one was really capture of the information.
Then step two was visualize the information.
So we caught all this information off
of all these instruments in the lab.
We then can visualize it.
We can see it.
We can decide whether
this gene's overexpressing or underexpressing.
And then downstream was the data mining.
How do we create value from the information?
And what's funny is I had
no background at all in biotech pharma.
I didn't know how to spell bioinformatics.
I think I might have went on Yahoo back
then and figured out what the hell it meant.
But truthfully, it really didn't matter.
At the end of the day,
we were building software for scientists.
And what mattered was, were we
creating value out of this invention?
So what you think about now, whether it
be that you are working in the energy industry,
whether you are building data,
whether you are building
drones that are capturing information,
whether you are building satellites
that are actually looking at,
let's say, methane emissions, at the end of the day,
the value very often comes from the data.
And that is the magic of it all.
And that's been the case truly in
a magnificent way over the past 20 years
and growing more and more so.
So what's fascinating is when I first had
the privilege of doing this class, this exact
lecture back in the old days with Joe and
Joost Bonson and that whole team, it was funny.
We were looking at business models that were so arcane.
It was basically, are you going to sell online?
Are you going to sell retail?
That was it.
And then you had a couple of nuances.
You had computer companies that, like Michael
Dell, competing against a company called Gateway.
And they're not going to sell.
And it was a whole other novel business model,
was that they would customize the computer
for you based on your specific specifications
versus everybody else that basically you walked
into your local equivalent of a Best Buy
and you bought the computer they had
there based on how much memory you needed.
But there was no customization.
So customization became a differentiating factor.
And these were very, very small incremental
changes that took place until we suddenly
saw ubiquitous Wi-Fi.
ubiquitous internet connectivity where we
saw now business models that could
never have existed just months or years
before suddenly came into play so what
I'm gonna do today is is share with
you and sort of where business models evolve
from and how important they are to
the decisions you guys make whether you be
the founder entrepreneur you be the
fifth higher in the company or you're
going to work for a big organization
and you happen to have the luxury of
launching a new product at the end of
the day a business model is not only
critical to the way the company
operates and communicates and brands itself to
the world but it also needs to
be flexible enough that it can adjust so
let's talk a little bit about these
things so sort of starting in the very
beginning of it you know choosing the
right business model is is crucial for
the success of any company and for those
of you that read some of the background
material for this course
one of the definitions is that
a successful business must be willing to
modify its model to adapt quickly
in any market and that's absolutely critical
that will define whether your business
is nimble and succeeds long-term or
maybe you got lucky and it was a blip
on the screen as a matter of fact from that
same book if you guys don't know how many
of you looked at it but it was part
of the reading of this course was
the business model generation book and this
model or this definition i
think is perfect a business model
describes the rationale of how
an organization creates delivers and
captures value that's it and the value
can be measured in many many different
ways hopefully it's measured on the
consumer side the customer side the
corporate side whoever you're ultimately selling
to whether it's a SAS platform
and you're selling enterprise-wide
solutions to the financial service
industry or you're delivering a product to
an end user a consumer so it's a
b2b versus a b2c
type of a model when we think
about frameworks and this is something that
you know when my career started was
in tech and then sort of in biopharma
Tech for many many years and then a
number of years back I started to move
over to the other side of the
equation which was investing in companies and
having been on the operating side
literally out there all the time raising
capital for companies expanding
hiring firing succeeding failing taking
companies from
price lines to demand from Process paus pull andhoggi로 usually
saying you canges in firings for failing taking companies from
from literally eight people up to
85 to 250 to 1,000 people,
all of that growth typically happens
because the organization is well-funded
and it has flexibility in its business model.
When I go back for
a moment to share with you
the company Molecularware, which was an MIT spinout,
that company was building bioinformatic software,
software for scientists.
It had one business model.
It sold to academics when I
arrived as CEO of that company.
It was my first CEO gig ever.
And of course they sold
to the people they knew, right?
These were all super smart people that came out of,
you know, the Rican Institute in Japan,
the Broad Institute, or at that time,
I guess it was the Whitehead Institute.
And that was the business model.
But you can't really scale very well,
nor can you be very, very attractive
to the investment community if you have one client
and that client is academics
or that one client is a business model.
That client is government.
So we started to think about other models.
Some of them we're gonna talk about today.
So we not only built software for scientists
and sold to the academicians,
which is an entirely different sales process, right?
You've got different budgetary processes,
different conferences you need to attend.
But then we developed a series of other sales mechanisms.
One of the first and most successful was
because we had relationships
with the Rican Institute in Japan,
we decided that we needed to do more
of a business model in Asia.
And certainly building a Salesforce in Asia
was out of the question
for a little Kendall Square company
with 15 people.
So we started partnering with distributors.
So we had this fantastic distribution partnership
with a company called CTC.
And CTC essentially sold our product for us.
So that became part of our business model.
So we had direct to academicians,
which was great because it
was like the name branding, right?
Like Harvard bought our software,
or Lawrence Berkeley, National Lab,
bought our software.
But then all of a sudden we started landing clients
in other parts of the
world that we could never touch.
We could never ever have afforded to put together
a Salesforce and management and training
to sell in Asia, as an example.
So distributors became a second part of our model.
And then as we started to build a little bit
of a brand for ourselves, we
said, how else can we sell?
We wanted to sell more
into the US and to Europe.
But again, building a big
Salesforce was not in our budget.
So we then looked at what's called OEM.
Who knows what that means?
Anybody?
Just yell it out.
Original equipment manufacturers.
So we realized, wait a minute, our software,
we wrote APIs to all these cool instruments,
Cartesian robots, bio robotics, Packard bioscience,
axon scanners, applied precision scanners.
Some of those people have really shitty software.
And they've got good instruments.
We've got amazing software.
We're not interested in building instruments.
Why don't we partner with them and bundle our software
inside of their instrument?
So we wound up landing one of our first deals
with Applied Precision in Issaquah, Washington.
And they had phenomenal imaging technology.
One of the best scanners at the time,
but really crappy software, hard to use,
kludgy, it was just a pain in the butt.
And ultimately they started selling more product
because they had a lot of software.
And they started selling more product
because now their software was seamless,
fully integrated into their instrument.
And it cost us nothing to sell.
Every time they sold an instrument,
we got a check in the mail.
So we went from direct to distributors, to OEM,
and then continued.
So having that experience as an operating person,
how to build these international
or these national organizations,
was really based on those experiences.
And now my job is, I invest in companies.
And I'm a company.
So we have a fund based out of London.
We invest throughout Europe and the UK and elsewhere.
We're doing a deal in Australia right now.
And our focus is about 70% health care,
and everything else is deep tech software,
SaaS platforms, robotics, all B2B.
So let's talk a little bit
about how we see the world.
This is also out of the
book that was part of this class,
which I thought was fantastic.
This is essentially nine of
the key ingredients, what they call
the canvas in that book.
The business model generation book was about,
how do you think about a business model?
And all of these slides will be available, of course,
so you don't have to kill yourself to take notes.
But I will say this.
When you think about each
of these slices of the pie,
of course, in reality, they're not all the same size.
They're going to change in size based
on where your company is from the standpoint
of its product development, its financing, et cetera.
But each of these components are so critical.
And very often, they blend together.
So you might have key resources or key activities
that are being overseen by one
of the managers in the company,
whereas the entire marketing department
is in charge of the value proposition
and trying to segment the customers.
But at the end of the
day, each one of these things
need to move harmoniously.
And if you think about the most successful companies,
and we're going to use a
couple of examples here today, they,
they have somehow figured out how
to take these nine little pieces of the pie
and have them move in a beautiful way together.
And that includes everything from value proposition
to the customer segments and then ultimately the cost
structure.
Because if you haven't modified and designed your cost
structure, ultimately, you're going to start to lose money,
which means you're not going
to be able to properly support
the client, which means you'll have no repeat business.
So each of these things are amazing.
For those in here that play instruments,
it is exactly that concept of
an orchestra or a jazz band.
It needs to flow together.
And if you get everything moving at the same time
and they're all moving with some great flow,
you create beautiful music.
If your oboe is way off
or your violinist is one beat behind,
things are just a little bit off.
And that creates this ripple effect,
these second and third order consequences that ultimately
impact the entire process.
And that's what we're going to talk about today.
So let's talk about the business models.
So the business models are the best companies
that have ever been able
to modify the best companies that
figured this out.
So taking a look a
little bit around how we think
about business models, this is nothing new to anybody here.
We're all consumers.
So all of us have
dealt with a gazillion different business
models, whether we even realize it or not.
Of course, subscription business models
seem to rule the day.
Subscription business models did not exist 15
years ago. There was nothing to subscribe to.
If I wanted to go watch a movie for
the weekend and I wanted to do it at home,
I got in my car and
I drove to this place called Blockbuster.
And I walked up and down the aisles,
it's about the size of a medium-sized CVS.
And I went to the adventure section
or the romance section or the comedy section.
And then I went up to the counter
and I had my three VCR tapes or DVDs
that I wanted to see that
weekend or that period of time.
And I brought that out. And I said,
I want to see this. That's what I'm doing.
Subscription business models didn't exist. Subscription business models didn't
exist 15 years ago. There was nothing to subscribe to.
home there was no subscription i never needed to
come back to that store again all of a sudden
subscription models started to make sense when you have
a new economy you have a new world where
people think less about owning and more
about experience right think about how companies like
zip car and others and there's a
gazillion different models of equivalent zip cars throughout
europe because people say why do i need to have a
car like in the old days you know and i'm talking
old days like 10 years 15 years ago if you
needed to rent a car it was a nightmare right you're
sitting in cambridge the closest car rental place might
be at logan airport you had to get there
then you had to go to the rental center zip car
comes along and boom they had a model where i can
actually find a car with my phone three blocks from
my house and i can return it to a similar
location so subscription really changed the world
but there's obviously other models here we're very
familiar with
uh we'll talk about different ones
at different times obviously the freemium model
all of us are familiar certainly the
app store has completely dominated our lives
uh whether you use an android or you use
an iphone uh everything's free uh for three days
and then we're going to charge you or everything's
free for seven days and then you're going to get
hit with 14.99 a month in perpetuity and we're
going to make it super hard for you to quit
so the freemium model really came into
place and this was mind-boggling in the investment
community not that long ago you're going to
give away your product and somehow you're going to
become a successful company so that's another way to
think about how do i get to the market which
one of these or two of these or three of
these am i gonna choose the marketplace certainly has taken
over think about the marketplace as the etsy's
of the world the ebay's of the world where
i can actually myself create a marketplace i can
sell cool t-shirts or i can wind up cleaning
my garage and selling a whole bunch of neat
things that are in there because I'm part of this
marketplace. The advertising world has completely changed.
It used to be dominated by big, big
advertising companies, quite truthfully. I mean, there
were these massive New York firms that worked
with big companies and those big companies had
huge advertising budgets and it was very, very linear.
You bought TV time, you bought ad time in
a magazine, so you're sitting there at the salon
flipping through People magazine and a commercial, or I
should say a page shows up and it's promoting
some new product. That was advertising. Advertising
now has completely transformed the way we live.
You're completely unaware how often we're impacted
by advertising. And certainly, as I mentioned
earlier, when I gave you the examples of
one of my earliest companies, direct sales, OEM, and
resellers. Truly foundational ways they've existed forever,
but they are still some of the most
important ways to think about getting your product
to the market. If you are building a product,
whether it be a software platform or it
be a technology instrument or it winds up being
a widget that actually helps people that
are photographers work better, you have to think
about how am I going to get this into the
most amount of hands as possible. And the OEM reseller
and essentially the direct sales market is still the
way to do it. Think about in the area of
pharmaceutical biotech. They still have direct sales forces.
Because doctors are busy, they don't have
time to watch advertising. They're certainly not signing
up to any freemium, they can only attend so
many conferences. So you need to physically be there
to actually educate them. So think about each of
these. In fact, everybody here using a laptop is
probably most familiar with the OEM model. Every one
of our laptops, you open it up and if you're
using a PC, it has a little sticker on
it, usually says Intel inside. That's ingenious. I've never
seen an Intel driven ahead. But I don't care,
gosh, I'm using them, but I don't care, right?
store in my entire life. They could care less
about who I am. They're not selling direct to
consumer, right? They don't care about B to C. They
don't even care about B to B. They care about
B to M, business to manufacturer. So they say,
I'm not going to sell to Johnson and Johnson,
or I'm not going to sell to Gillette or Fidelity and
try to get them to buy a bunch of Intel stuff
for their computers. I'm going to sell to Dell.
I'm going to sell to ThinkPad. I'm going to sell
to the manufacturer. They're going to do all the
work for me. So the magic that we actually have
in the world of technology is that we have
so many options, which is fantastic. So think about
different business model examples that just touch you
every day, whether it be new clothing you buy,
your Apple Watch or your iPhone, a laptop that
you purchased, or some sort of a service that
you recently picked up.
Because you read something great about it on
your phone. So let's talk about different industries
and sub-industries, because there's lots of ways to
think about business models. So the first two
examples I'm going to give you are really known
to you, of course. And then we're going to talk
about industry specifics. So the number one example
I think all of us know is Netflix.
So for those of you
that remember, anybody here remember Blockbuster?
I find every year, Joe,
the number of hands goes down.
I'm getting really old, but this class stays about
the same age. So the number of hands keeps going
down. But Blockbuster was absolutely amazing. They
owned the world when it came to video.
And even when things went to DVD, they
still had all of that physical real estate.
And then the guys at Netflix came along. In fact,
there was a slide I used to use in this
presentation. And it was actually a billboard that
was on Route 101 outside of San Francisco.
And it said, follow your
dreams. We used to mail DVDs.
Netflix. And that's what they did. The guys
at Netflix figured out, geez, the idea of owning
500 or 1,000 shops in strip malls around
the United States, manning them with human beings,
worrying about security, inventory, shipping, receiving
returns. Oh my god, that's exhausting.
Why don't we just put a bunch of
warehouses around the United States loaded up with DVDs?
And when people want a movie,
we just mail it to them. And if they keep it
for a day, so what? If they keep it for 10 days,
we don't really care. We'll just literally print
another movie. So that transformed the entire way
that all of us thought about movie rental back then.
Now keep in mind, it was a sign of the times.
There was no bandwidth. If you wanted to download
a movie when Netflix first came out and started
shipping DVDs in an envelope, if you
wanted to download a normal feature-length film,
it could take six, seven,
hours to download. It would take two to three
times the length of the movie to download it
to your computer. It would eat up all
of your memory, and then you would watch it,
and then you would delete it, and then you
would do it again. So they realized this download stuff
is just not for us. We're going to send
people DVDs on demand. Everybody in the world ran out
and bought a DVD player. So for
companies building DVD players, it was awesome.
They were like, oh my
god, this is heaven. Netflix literally,
they built the DVD industry. So that
was their business model. Convenience, no late fees,
two days after you order it on a Tuesday,
bang, it's at your house on Wednesday or Thursday. You
watched it over the weekend. Maybe you shared it
with some friends, and then you sent it back
in an envelope. It was amazing. And they
then created a little bit of a subscription service,
where if you paid a certain amount per
month, you were able to, at any one time,
have three or four DVDs. And that's what they did. And
they built the DVD industry. And they built the DVD industry.
So they were able to have three DVDs. Or if you
paid a tiny bit more per month, you were able to have
five or six or seven DVDs, which is great, if you
have a family that's got a bunch of kids who are
watching one thing, or you have parents that
might be watching something else. So they were essentially
doing direct-to-consumer mailing, and they created
subscriptions. And then the world changed.
Netflix, like Blockbuster, could have easily
gone bust. There's no more Blockbusters.
But Netflix
could have easily gone bust. But they figured
out that if we incorporate technology, we can
begin to stream movies. They didn't abandon their
old business model. They slowly moved into the
streaming service. And people were like, this is
fantastic. But it's the same company, right? Before
they used to send me a DVD. Now I hit a
button, and now it streams to me. Sometimes you have a
little buffering issue, but it's okay, right? And this
is quite a few years ago. Who would have
thought Netflix,
which was a company that shipped DVDs and
offered streaming with lots of buffering and slow points,
would become what it is today? Think
about the business model that Netflix has today.
What does Netflix do when you think about
them as a company, forgetting about their original
business for a minute? How do they make money?
Who are they competing with now? They were competing
with just Blockbuster. That was it.
Tell me what you know about Netflix.
I hope you enjoyed the podcast. If you did, please share me
a like, and I'll see you in the next episode of My Business.
I'm going to be back next week with
another issue. I'll see you then. Take care, everybody.
Bye-bye.
know about Netflix besides the fact that you
can go onto your Netflix app on your smart
TV or on your iPhone or iPad and watch
a movie or download it for your plane ride? Besides
that, what do they do? They produce movies.
Can you imagine the CEO of Netflix back in
the days when he was shipping DVDs to
people's homes telling his investors, you know, someday
I really want to compete against Hollywood. You
know, Paramount, MGM, I think I want to
compete against them. They would have thought,
dude, you're completely out of your mind.
You ship DVDs. This is basically a mail order
company. They have now become one of the most
powerful producers of content in the world.
They're winning awards left and right and
crushing all of the old-fashioned movie production.
crushing all of the old-fashioned movie production
companies and TV production companies. What else do
they do? What is something new? Go ahead.
As of February 1st, we raised
every subscription price by $1 or $2.
All $300 million.
And even beyond that, they then
introduced the password protection non-sharing policy.
All of the investment community.
And it was like, oh my god, they're
going to get crushed. People are going to run.
They increased the number of subscriptions. The
day they announced no more password sharing,
they're increasing subscriptions over the following
week with something like 18 million
new subscribers. Because now I can't give my password
out to my friend and my kid and my
kid who gives it to his girlfriend. Now all of
a sudden they're all like, oh shit, I'll just open
my own account.
So these incremental increases in subscription, right, which
is really hard to do. But once it is
literally part of your life, you're not going to
give that up. And then on top of that, without
even increasing prices, they increase revenue and
number of subscribers exponentially just by saying,
this password sharing thing has to be very
limited. So that is something else that they
have done, right? Which I guess you could
say it's not necessarily a new business model,
as much as it is tweaking and fine-tuning
an existing business model to become more profitable
without punishing the customer very much,
right? They didn't double their prices.
They essentially said, ah, you know, normal cost
of business increase, but you can't share your
password. And most people knew I shouldn't be
sharing my password anyways, right? So they didn't
lose anybody. They gained something like 18 million.
Think about this. They have just hit 300
million subscribers.
This week, it was just announced.
Yeah. So you've got a company that now has,
we're talking about the population of the United States.
I don't know, what are we at as
a country? 400, something like that? 300 million people
are subscribers and pay every single month,
whether they watch a movie or not.
I mean, how awesome is that? And on top
of that, they now have a market capitalization of
400 million subscribers. So that's a lot of money.
And they're not going to be able to do that.
180 billion people say, good. By
ese, roughly this, that's, that's amazing.
But I think it's incredible that
we that these companies at companiesfigure that,
you know, 50 and 60 million get from the company.
It's unbelievable that the coming years when
concrete blast alerts are Sue US should take
nightgown to suntan and the
Come on over here.
we shaping marry las Vegas.
I'd live 700,000 people that'd been stricken.
It's ridiculous.
I want to memories.
The evidence makes.
It'sLord before is.
100 billion did this really?
market cap. It's mind-boggling when you think
about it. But something else that they've done,
because they keep changing their model, right? They
got into producing TV shows. They then got
into producing movies, then TV shows. They now
have some of the world's best actors, actresses
chasing them. Can I get in your next show? Years ago,
no actor wanted to be in a TV show. If you
went from commercials to TV to movies, you
never went back. I'm not doing a series.
It has to a point now where you've got
people like Nicole Kidman, top actors and actresses saying,
are you guys doing a series? I would love to do
a series. How cool is that? I get to do 20 seasons,
five seasons, 50 episodes, whatever the number
is. It's absolutely incredible the impact that
they've had on the industry and on Hollywood.
And they started off mailing DVDs. That was
their business model. Something new that
they've done, live events, never before.
Something else?
That's a really excellent point. It goes
back to what we talked about earlier, right?
It's great that you have software that does A, B,
and C, makes life easier. It's cool that I can
actually search the hell out of this massive
library of movie options. But it's actually using
technology, deep learning, data mining, AI now,
to help me find things that are
more relevant based on my own feedback, whether I gave
it a thumbs up or a thumbs down after I
watched a movie. They know if you started watching a
movie and then you killed it and you never went
back to it. I mean, there's so much
data. So what you have there is more personalization,
which to use an old term is stickiness, right?
It's like, of course I'm going to keep using this
because they've made my life easier.
And now they're doing the live events.
Think about what you're seeing now. They have
done fights. They have done a number of
other type of live events. That starts to
really be interesting. I mean, could we be watching
the Super Bowl on Netflix in five years?
You just watched the NFL Christmas game.
Yep. Absolutely. The Tyson fight. Think about
that. So they are essentially modifying change
in their business model. They're a great example.
Next one, of course, is the business model.
And I'm going to talk about the business model.
Of course, it's Google. This is easy. I mean,
you've got a company here. And I think this is
really the one that I should refer to
when I talk about market cap versus GDP.
Not so much Netflix, but 2.4
trillion market cap. That's a whack-a-doodle.
It doesn't even make sense. And
what did they start off doing? Search.
That was it. They were going to build
a better search algorithm because there were a whole
bunch of really smart people out
of Stanford and elsewhere that said,
search sucks. This just doesn't make sense. And
humans aren't going to learn Boolean logic and
put quotes here, a plus sign, plus this asterisk.
We need to come up with better ways of searching.
So they brought technology in
and increased the value of search.
And that's all they were. It was another search
company. And for those of us that remember those
days, there was Lycos, Yahoo. Gosh,
I can't remember all the names.
Amazing.
I mean, I think Lycos was a Boston company, right?
Unbelievable. And I remember at the time
thinking, do we need another search engine?
I mean, this doesn't even make sense. They
crushed the search space and they could have
stopped there and still been relevant. But then
they moved into other parts of the world. What
are some of the other things that they
have done from a standpoint of transformative business model
changes that makes Google relevant? How
else do all of us use Google?
Or most of us?
Google Drive.
Google Docs, Google Drive. I don't
have to think about documents. Basically,
I can go on a Google Drive, boom, use
their Excel spreadsheet, save it, live action. My team,
most of which is based in Europe, can all
work on the same Excel spreadsheet at the same time,
and it's instantly changing. We don't
have to keep version 1.1, version 2.25,
then I send it off to this person who
makes some other version, and then we're missing the changes
done by somebody over the next 10 years. So, yeah,
that's a big change. And then, you know, we're not
going to be able to do it again. We're going to have
to keep it up. We're going to have to keep it up.
But I think that's the key. I think that's the
key. I think that's the key. I think that's the key.
Absolutely incredible, right? So
that became another subscription model,
another way they demonstrated their prowess
in technology. What else does Google do?
Google Voice or Google Maps, both of
which I use 12,000 times a day.
Exactly. So think about Google Maps, right?
Cool, free, right? The data analytics behind
Google Maps is where all the value is. They
know more about the Earth than most anyone. They know
geography. They know which ships are moving in the
ocean. They know more about us than anyone in
the world, whether it be the fact that we
searched something, and they now know that about us.
Google has an entire group devoted
to health, global health, that integrates
with global health organizations like the NIH. If
there is an increase in the number of searches,
let's say, in the big world,
Google pronunciation,
Pacific Northwest around particular symptoms,
runny nose, head, fever, puking, you name it.
Let's say little kid symptoms.
Once Google starts to see that trend,
then in the Pacific Northwest, let's say Seattle,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
they're starting to see this.
That becomes a biomarker.
That becomes a data point.
And they track that.
And then they can share it with health organizations
because they know that the flu this year
hit that part of the region really hard.
And what does that mean?
Well, it has this ripple effect of power
where it's like, that's cool to know,
but what if we also let clinicians know,
especially pediatricians?
What if we're able to then communicate,
sell our data to groups like PPD
or some of the big pharmaceutical biotech
companies like Johnson & Johnson
that make over-the-counter medicine
for kids suffering from the flu or vomiting
or whatever it is, right?
Think about that.
It is an entire shift in how data collected
from a company that did nothing but search
now actually transforms the way health is actually treated.
And when you start to see severe illnesses,
you start to see things that are scary,
that information is then communicated to the NIH.
So every year we make new flu vaccines.
They've got a pretty good high probability of working
because many of them, you know,
they're designed for multiple strains,
but sometimes it just doesn't work so well.
Once they're able to identify there's a new strain
or a strain that is resistant to a vaccine
given in that particular region, action can be taken.
Think about that.
It's absolutely mind boggling.
Think about the fact that
they're able to use their satellites
and Google Earth and other things to actually help people,
predict whether.
There are companies in the financial service sector,
I spent two years myself at
a big hedge fund in Connecticut.
We looked at data from everywhere.
I mean, I'm talking Google data.
We looked at Palantir data and we made bets,
currency bets and other things based on the fact
that we were able to collect data from,
let's say public and non-public sources around the world.
If I'm able to see trends in a particular area,
I'm able to actually make decisions.
How do we predict or how
do we know how many cars
are gonna be sold in Q2 of this year?
Registrations.
Perhaps registrations, yeah.
If I ask you how
do we know how many cars
were sold in Q4 of
last year, how do we know?
Registrations.
Because what?
What do we know?
Yeah, but also financial reports, right?
The CEO stood up at his
annual meeting at the end of Q4
and said, we're very proud to announce that blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, and this number of SUVs
versus this and profitability.
It's almost ancient data at that point.
It's completely useless.
You cannot buy a stock
based on how many cars GM,
Ford, Tesla sold last quarter.
Trailing data is useless.
What if I could use satellite information
to actually see how many cars
are being shipped out of Japan
every single day of the year?
Because I could tell you this,
that if there's less ships leaving the port in Japan
that happens to be producing all of these Japanese cars
as one example, or German cars, you name it,
I can guarantee you that
sales will be down next quarter.
But nobody reports on this stuff.
Right?
لأن
The car dealers know things are slowing down.
Interest rates have gone up.
Perhaps consumers are being more conservative
because we have inflation.
So they're keeping their car a couple years longer.
None of that shows up in
the sales data today or yesterday.
But if you're a car dealer like a Herb Chambers
and you're looking at your 15 dealerships
and you're looking out of your lot
and you're seeing umpteen cars sitting there
and you think to yourself,
geez, in Q1 we would have sold this many
and in Q3 it went down and
in Q4 it went down a little bit.
What the hell does that mean?
Well, they do not want Nissan
to suddenly deliver them another 90 cars.
So they call their Nissan rep and they say,
we're gonna cut it back to 40 this quarter.
We'll push the old shit we have on the lot.
But nobody in Wall Street knows that shit
until the end of the
quarter when the CEO comes out
and says, we sold less cars.
Can you imagine?
You're able to use satellite technology
to actually track the number of ships carrying cars
and actually predict the future.
Now that's a business model.
That's the kind of stuff
that data is able to do.
So when you think about your company,
think about your business model,
your first business model might be simple.
You're shipping DVDs.
You're selling this widget
to companies that do presentations.
You're selling this software to a logistics company.
And that logistics company is going to increase productivity
by 15%.
But be prepared because your business model needs to change.
You need to become more
valuable to your client, more sticky,
and more relevant all of the time.
So I'll stop there with those two examples.
And then just let's talk about a few other industries.
Real quick, stop for questions, feedback, comments,
anything really crazy I said that doesn't make sense.
All right, let's keep moving.
Let's talk about a couple of industries.
And this goes again back to our original pie chart
that came out of this great
book that's part of this class,
which is you've got these nine different things
that you have to think about.
And every industry itself is different.
If you're in pharmaceutical,
that's a hell of a lot different
than the diagnostics industry.
And if you're in the diagnostic space,
it's a heck of a lot
different than the med tech space.
Like the med tech people
are basically selling medical technologies.
It might be hips.
It might be knees.
It might be an instrument sitting on a desk.
The diagnostic people are actually selling tests.
The pharmaceutical people, whether
they're biotech or pharma,
if they're really core biotech, they're building stuff
and they don't sell anything.
And then they're hoping that
stuff at phase two or phase
three gets acquired by pharma.
And then pharma pushes it
out to their massive sales teams.
So each of those within the life science sector
all have a different business model.
So one example I wanted to
give is sort of med tech.
Because being at MIT, I
spoke to one of the panelists
that was up here earlier who's doing a company that,
or brand new company that's going to be spinning out
of one of the labs here, Bob Langer's lab.
And when you think about that new technology,
like right now, we're just
trying to make proof of concept.
But when it gets out into the market,
how do you ultimately sell it is really critical.
Because in fields like med tech, healthcare, life sciences,
you not only need to
have the greatest whiz bang stuff,
but you need to think about adoption.
You need to think about how
do I get the most influential,
influential prescribers, doctors, clinicians, surgeons,
pediatricians, oncologists to do this and look at it,
and then tell their friends at the next conference
they speak at that there's a new surgical instrument
that they're using.
So in this world of med tech, as an example,
and some of you all raised your hands earlier
that you're in that field of life sciences,
you have a problem that most other industries don't have.
You need to be able to first make things
work, make sure that it's both efficacious and safe, right?
It works, but it doesn't kill anybody.
It's probably a good combination.
But even though you have a great product that works
and it didn't kill anybody,
nobody might write a prescription for it.
No doctor may ever even use it.
And depending what kind of doctors you're dealing with,
holy shit, then your business model is even more challenged.
Because if you're dealing with surgeons,
they're pretty cutting edge.
They love the newest gadgets.
If you're dealing with psychiatrists,
probably not so quick to adopt new technology.
They're still using DSM-5 to actually predict
what the particular disorder is or disease
that their patient has.
And then they're prescribing very often off-label drugs
or drugs that are off patent.
So you have different types of users.
Those are the people you're selling to.
So you have to think about that.
In the med tech world,
your business model is absolutely critical
because not only do you have to make something
that doesn't kill people or makes their life better
and really works, but you also have to figure out
how on earth am I gonna
be able to pay for this?
Are they gonna be able to pay for it?
Is this gonna be a direct-to-consumer?
All of us open up
our phone and we get advertisements
for this gut microbiome test
and we get advertisement for something else,
you know, know your ancestry
and you'll be able to better manage your future health.
Or if you're a person suffering with,
cardiovascular issues,
you may see something on a commercial.
But at the end of the day,
if your doctor doesn't write a prescription
for that new medication, it just doesn't sell.
So when you think about your business model,
it's really important to think about
who are the constituents I need to convince, right?
It's not as easy as selling
cool t-shirts on eBay or Amazon,
where I'm just hoping it's cool enough
that people will buy it.
And if it doesn't, I don't
really have a lot of overhead.
It is a complex industry.
It's like selling SaaS platforms to the automotive industry.
The automotive industry doesn't move very fast.
It doesn't change very quickly.
And because it's very big and powerful,
it probably is hard to get an automotive company
to put new technology into its system
because everything's working just the way it is.
It's just a matter of time.
It's not going to be the way it is.
Yeah, we can make it a little more efficient,
but we kind of like our
procurement process the way it is.
If you want to sell them to that industry,
you need to think about who are the constituents
I'm selling to versus, let's say,
an industry that is right at the cutting edge, right?
Software companies that are looking to tweak
the finest little bit of value
out of how their disparate teams communicate.
They're going to download that app.
They're going to try it out.
They're going to do things
at a speed and a pace
that you wouldn't normally expect.
The challenge is that there might be high switching cost.
So you've got a challenge there, right?
Like all of us today, we could
sign up for an AT&T contract today
and get our discounted iPhone and so forth.
Then a year from now, we
decide we're going to go to T-Mobile.
Maybe we have to pay a fee.
No stress.
Keep your number.
Go to T-Mobile.
So that's high switching cost for the company,
low switching cost.
And if I'm the one buying
stuff, I like low switching costs.
If I join this fancy Equinox fitness center
and I'm not locked into a two-year contract
and I can quickly move over to something else
and go to LA Fitness,
that's low switching cost for me.
I like that.
But for them, it sucks, right?
Because they might have tremendous turnover.
So you have to think about that as well.
Who am I selling to?
What is the differentiation?
And how do I get
them to keep coming back forever?
Because if for me to be competitive in my industry,
I have to have no contract, right?
Think about some of these
new mobile phone companies out there.
Who can think about what are
a couple of the names you hear
that are some of these new fangled phone companies
out there, one of which is represented
by a very famous actor?
Mint Mobile.
And there's a few others.
Consumer Cellular.
I feel like that's a good one.
I'm going to go through this.
Think about it.
Does anybody here know who Mint Mobile uses
for their entire network?
T-Mobile.
Why would that be?
Think to yourself, holy shit.
Mint Mobile is using the T-Mobile network.
Why would they do that?
Because T-Mobile realized that there's
a different level of consumer that
might want the flexibility of bring
your device, no contracts, short-term contracts,
super cheap on a monthly basis.
But you're not going to be able to download
as quickly as you want.
There's going to be some restrictions around bandwidth.
But your roommate, who's a T-Mobile customer,
is probably paying $70 more a month.
And they have ubiquitous connectivity.
That's a business model.
Think about that.
T-Mobile has a business model.
AT&T has a business model.
They're almost identical.
Verizon has a business model.
In the UK, my phone is a Virgin mobile carrier.
That's their business model.
But T-Mobile said, huh, there's
an entire part of the market
that we cannot even touch.
Because the way we operate in the big stores
is one-year contracts, fancy phones, lock your ass in,
and we're going to charge you a fortune.
And they got smart.
They got smart.
So what you think about is, even companies
that have a great business model that's succeeding, in order
for them to capture an
entirely new part of the market,
they might have to reinvent themself.
Or they create a new brand that they own.
What's another example?
Think about this in other industries, not tech, maybe
tech, of brands you know
that were known for one thing,
perhaps.
And now they've got multiple brands under the same umbrella
to serve different consumers.
What's an example?
How about in the automotive industry?
Toyota.
Who is it?
And Lexus, but I'm not Toyota.
And Toyota, right?
So Lexus and Toyota, right?
So think about that.
Toyota dominated forever.
But it was considered like the car you bought,
middle of the road, safe, reliable.
They knew they were never going
to get the up and coming
kick-ass researcher who was making $50,000 a year
and is now making $450,000 a year at Novartis.
That dude, that woman, they were not buying a Toyota.
They were buying the Mercedes, where
they were buying something else, the Cadillac, whatever
it was at the time.
Toyota realized, we have an entire part of the market
that we cannot even reach.
And they created Lexus.
Nissan.
What did Nissan create?
Infiniti.
Same thing.
What did Volkswagen create?
Acura.
Audi was an independent brand.
They may own it now.
Who the hell knows?
They created Acura.
Acura is an automotive.
Is it what is it?
It's an automotive.
Oh, yes, you're right.
Absolutely.
Was it Audi?
I thought Volkswagen created a different brand.
It's called Volkswagen.
Oh, that's right.
They did.
And that's just different.
That's a consolidation in the industry.
But when you think about some of these brands,
think about brands that we all wear every day.
Think about Ralph Lauren as a brand.
What's under the umbrella of Ralph Lauren?
What's at the high level
and lowest level of Ralph Lauren?
Does anybody know?
Have you heard of the brand called Loren?
Google it.
Loren.
It's like their bespoke, tailored $900 for a jacket.
The next level down is Polo by Ralph Lauren.
Do you know there's actually a level above Loren?
It's called a purple label.
It is made to order couture level under Ralph Lauren.
You know where it is
all the way at the bottom?
Polo Sport.
Which is still a great product.
But if you're just looking
for a cheap sweatshirt or zip-up,
Polo Sport works great.
And it's part of the Ralph Lauren brand.
If you're at the next level, you're
buying the cute little horse on your shirt,
the $95, $110 zip-up sweater with the horse,
Polo by Ralph Lauren.
You could buy a really nice jacket for $200.
The next level, Loren.
The next level, Perl.
Perl.
Purple.
Think about that.
They own your entire life.
You became loyal to the brand
when you were 17 years old
and all you could afford was Polo Sport.
You thought it was so cool.
And now you're at the next level and you're still
loyal to the brand.
That's the beauty of companies,
that think about business model
every single day and what is the market segment
that we can capture next.
So let's move along a little bit.
Digital commerce has always changed.
It's changing.
I'm going to blast through these
because this stuff you guys know.
But when I think about digital commerce,
because it's changed so much, not only because bandwidth
has increased, but now with the intervention of AI,
which we'll talk about, you've
got all of these new models
that were created.
Think about Uber.
Really owns no cars.
Airbnb doesn't own any hotel rooms,
but they have more rooms controlled
than the top three hotel companies in the world combined.
That sharing economy suddenly became very, very valuable.
The personalized economy is pretty incredible too.
It's I've got a subscription to this and consumers say,
you know what surprised me, I'll try that out.
I'll take a shot because I
already subscribed to this particular brand.
I'll try it.
Think about companies like Rent the Runway.
I'll pay my subscription.
I get this beautiful dress or
five of them in the, you know,
I'll try it.
I'll pay my subscription.
I get this beautiful dress or
five of them in the, you know,
I'll try it.
I'll pay my subscription.
You know, sent to me.
I'll try it.
If I don't like it, I just send it back.
It's not the sharing economy, right?
But it is this personalized economy.
They know my style.
I get it sent to me.
Entirely different models, but they work so well.
Certainly the replenishment economy is
actually taking off more and more.
And these are driven by the
smart sensors in all of our lives.
These are the things that when
you sign up for your Amazon account
and you do an Amazon subscription,
think about that's a replenished economy.
Right?
I know that every 30 days I
need another box of Cascade for my dishwasher.
Or I need another, you know, something or
other that will be delivered to me automatically.
I don't have to think about it anymore.
Refrigerators are now using RFID and all sorts
of other tags where you're going to be able
to barcode scan the things that are in your refrigerator.
And when you're out, it just
goes on to your shopping list.
It's the replenish economy.
That's an entirely cool business model.
Versus the I run out of shit
and go to the supermarket economy, right?
Which is pretty much how I live still.
I make a little list.
Ah, shit, I'm out of those things again.
I put it on the list and then
at the end of the week or month,
I might go over to the supermarket and buy it.
I'd much prefer it show up to my house.
So think about those little
tweaks in business models really work.
And certainly, the do it for me service economy,
everything has exploded.
Everything from, I mean, my shirts get dirty.
I put them in a bag.
I hang it outside my door.
There's a little guy in a van shows up,
boom, takes him twice a week and brings other stuff
back.
But that has now accelerated into a
lot of other industries where people are basically
getting services that only the rich could
afford 50 or 20 or 30 years ago.
And now anybody can do it.
Think about home cleaning services.
When I was young, no one had a
maid unless they were really, really, really rich.
They had a cleaning person.
Then all of a sudden,
it became more and more common.
And now every time I open up my phone, there's
a new ad for some service, whether it be handyman
or it be cleaning people, I can get
my car waxed and detailed in my driveway.
So think about whatever you guys are building.
How am I going to get to my consumer?
Who do I have to convince?
How do I scale?
How do I change as times change?
And then I'm going to have to do it.
I'm going to have to do it.
The hospitality industry, I think,
is one of the most fun.
For a gazillion years, we've
all basically just used travel agents.
We would go online and we'd book our trip.
We'd go and search, what are the flights?
What is this?
What is that?
Before you know it, we pull together our trip.
Nowadays, what you're seeing is
these incredible technologies allowing us.
You can use ChatGPT and
say, act as a travel agent.
Design me a six-day trip in Rome.
I'm very interested in museums.
I'm interested in science.
I'm interested in academia.
I am not interested in any family events.
And I want it to be within this particular area.
Boom.
We have that in front of us.
So the travel industry has been transformed by technology.
And now we're talking about
things like co-robots in the future.
You know, renewable tourism events.
What you also have is space tourism.
Things that we never dreamed of before.
There's a company that I'm involved with
that's in Spain that literally builds these massive,
bigger than this room, like giant monster helium balloons.
And they have this capsule.
And it goes to whatever orbit it particularly goes to.
You can see the entire curvature of the Earth.
Who would have thought that would be a business model?
But you have companies that are creating
new technologies and new business models and becoming
very, very successful because of
the changes in that industry.
And AI will change everything.
So I'm going to close
with a few comments on this.
When you think about AI, which I think
is touching all of our lives, whether you're
in med tech, you're in energy,
think about this entire value chain, right?
Most of us, including myself, when I
think about AI, I think about like NVIDIA.
They're on the back end somewhere.
And I'm using chat GPT.
Or I'm using someone else's GPT.
But when you're thinking about
your company, where do you fit?
If you're an AI company or you're just a
company using AI to reach new markets, where do you
fit?
I mean, the data center infrastructure
is a phenomenal area right now.
And it's not just big data centers.
There's a company in Europe that
we do diligence the hell out of.
We ultimately passed on it.
But they're building massive data centers in Norway.
The weather there happens to be...
Yeah.
It's pretty cold and dark most of the year.
A fantastic place to put
a massive five-football field-sized data center.
Lots of land, very cool air, low
cost from the standpoint of air conditioning.
So think about like, hey, data centers, that's
a business, but that's not a business model.
Data centers in Norway using renewable energies
with funding from the government, now we're
starting to talk about a business model.
And a contract with Nvidia that gives us
these particular computers that are able to actually
process.
So think about where you want to be.
Most people are actually at the app side.
That's certainly where I think of, right?
As a consumer, what app can I use
that's going to be powered by this infrastructure?
So OpenAI, we're all familiar with, and Anthropic,
and Azure, and then you've got the cloud companies
like AWS, all of which are the data center side.
And then you've got all of the apps.
In fact, we even...
We even go to the next level.
If you take a look at AI tools and
revenues, what you ultimately see is that here's just
a snapshot, right?
Chat GPT on the left,
all the way to Pertori, Leonardo.ai.
I use this thing called Otter.
Anybody ever hear of Otter?
Isn't that the coolest thing I'm telling you?
I'm actually able to sit in meetings, and
I'm in a lot of Zoom meetings, and actually
pay attention.
Whereas before, I was
like listening, writing, listening, writing.
I was going...
I was trying to be like my own scribe.
Or I'd have someone from my office would
dial in the meeting, and that was their job.
Now Otter.ai, Otter.ai just joins the meeting.
That's it.
It sits in the background, and it transcribes
every single word that's being said in the
meeting.
And as soon as the voice
of the person changes, it turns...
It changes to speaker two,
speaker four, speaker two, speaker seven.
It's absolutely incredible.
And then it uses AI.
So it's not just a transcript, right?
Like a transcript has limited value.
I don't really want to read an hour-long meeting.
I don't want to read an hour-long meeting.
I don't want to read an hour-long meeting transcript.
It then uses AI, and
it creates a summary for me.
And then it creates an action item for me.
So it can hypothesize from the
meeting what actions were to be taken.
PowerPoint presentation to be sent, Excel
spreadsheet to be reviewed, follow-up email
related to meeting in June.
It's absolutely incredible.
So on the app side, the opportunities are incredible.
And being able to use and leverage
AI is going to change your life.
So let me end with this sort of pitfalls.
Don't overcomplicate things.
Make sure that you really understand the market dynamics.
I probably gave a lot of
examples, whether it be MedTech or others.
And really be flexible.
The companies that survive are the ones that
see the future, and they really think about
changing.
So you have to be adaptable.
And thank you very much for listening.
We appreciate it.
Bye bye.